Happy birthday!
生日快樂！
Rach, come on.
瑞秋，別這樣
It's your birthday!
是你的生日耶！
Hey...
嘿…
She's not as pretty as she was when she was 29.
她不像她29歲時那麼漂亮
Ms. Greene wants to establish some ground rules before she comes out.
在葛林小姐出來之前 她要先把幾件事說清楚
Please don't use the words "old" or "downhill"...
她希望你們不要用到如「老」 或者「走下坡」等字眼…
or "They still look pretty damn good."
或是「它們看來還是很棒」
They do.
它們還是
Rachel, come on out.
瑞秋，出來
Monica made breakfast.
摩妮卡做了早餐
Chocolate chip pancakes.
巧克力碎片鬆餅
We've got presents.
我們有禮物給你
Good ones?
好的禮物？
They're all from the list you gave us two weeks ago.
都是兩星期前你給的單子上的
Can I keep the presents and still be 29?
我可以只收禮物 而仍然是29歲嗎？
Come on, Rach, turning 30 is not that big a deal.
瑞秋，30歲沒什麼大不了
Really? Is that how you felt when you turned 30?
真的？你滿30時也是這麼覺得嗎？
Why, God, why?
為什麼，上帝，為什麼？
We had a deal. Let the others grow old, not me!
我們講好的了 讓其他人變老，我不要！
You guys, is it just me? Am I overreacting?
只有我這樣嗎？是我反應過度嗎？
No, it's not just you. My 30th birthday sure wasn't much fun.
不，不是只有你 我的30歲生日也不好過
And now Chandler!
現在是錢德了！
We're all getting so old.
我們都變得這麼老
Why are You doing this to us?
你為什麼這樣對我們？
The One Where They All Turn Thirty
本集播出：步入三十大關
rainystar壓制iPod-MP4
（瑞秋30歲生日快樂）
You're in a great place in your life. You have an amazing job, good friends.
你的生活過得很好 你有很棒的工作，很好的朋友
Your roommate's a soap opera star.
你的室友是連續劇明星
Your character is in a coma.
你的角色在昏迷中
I promised myself I wouldn't cry at this one.
我答應自己這個生日一定不哭
I know my life's going pretty well, but I see so many people...
我知道我目前過得很好 但我看到一些人…
who've accomplished their goals before they're 30.
在30歲以前 就完成了他們的目標
Yeah, but you shouldn't compare yourself to me.
是啊，你不應該和我比
-Come on, Phoebe! -You can do it!
-來，菲比！ -你做得到的！
-Come on. -There you go.
-來 -好了
I did it! One mile on a Hippity Hop.
我成功了！在跳跳球上走了一里
That's everything I wanted to do before I was 30.
30歲前我想完成的事
Except I wanted to patch things up with my sister.
除了我想和我妹修好關係
Oh, well. But, yeah!
嗯，可是
Girls, this thing is a godsend, if you know what I mean.
女人，這東西是上帝給的禮物 如果你懂我的意思
Let's have some fun. What do you want to do?
來做點有趣的事吧，你想做什麼？
Nothing. I don't want to do anything.
什麼也不做，我什麼也不想做
Doing nothing on your 30th is better than doing something stupid, like Ross.
在30歲生日時什麼都不做 總比做笨事好，像羅斯一樣
That was a practical purchase.
那是很實際的一項購買
I needed that car for transportation.
我需要那車子做交通工具
Okay? I have a child.
好嗎？我有小孩
How hot do I look in this?
我在這車裡看來很拉風吧？
Ross, a sports car?
羅斯，一台跑車？
Wouldn't it be cheaper to just stuff a sock down there?
在褲子裡塞襪子不是比較便宜？
That's not what this is about.
這不是為了那個
I am a sports car enthusiast.
我是跑車熱愛者
-I've always been into cars. -What's the horsepower?
-我一直都很喜歡車 -它的馬力多少？
I don't know, but look how shiny!
不知道，你看它多亮呀！
-I can't believe you bought this. -So can I have a ride, stud?
-你竟然買了這台車 -帥哥，載我一程吧？
Hop in.
跳上車
Get ready for the smoothest ride of your life.
準備好你這輩子最穩的一程
Damn it.
可惡
Okay, who's next?
好了，下一個是誰？
I am gonna do something today. I won't sit around like some old lady.
今天我一定要做點什麼 我不要像老太太一樣閒坐在這兒
I want to get something pierced.
我要在身上打個洞
Like my nose or my tongue or something.
像是鼻子、舌頭，或是別的地方
Really? Because that hurts.
真的？那會痛的
So what? The way I see it..
那又怎麼？我是這麼想…
Son of a bitch!
該死的！
Look, I know what you're going through.
我知道你經歷的
I'm totally freaked out about turning 25.
我25歲生日時嚇壞了
Get out of my apartment.
離開我家
Rach, I think that you're doing great.
瑞秋，你做的很好
Let's face it, no one handles this well.
正視事實吧，沒有人能真的 好好處理這件事
Least of all you.
至少你不行
Put that back on. Monica will be here any minute.
放回去，摩妮卡隨時會到家
But it hurts my Joey's apple.
可是喬伊的蘋果會痛
For the last time, it's not named after each individual man.
告訴你最後一次 它不是以每一個人的名字命名的
You've done a wonderful job with the party. Everything's so lovely.
錢德，你把宴會辦得真好 每樣東西都很美麗
Well, not as lovely as you.
沒有像你這麼美麗
I can't believe you have a 30-year-old daughter.
不能相信你有位30歲的女兒
And I can't believe you have a tux that's 30 years old.
不能相信你有件30歲的燕尾服
It's older than that. Ross was conceived right near this tuxedo.
這比30年還老 羅斯是在這件燕尾服旁有的
Everybody hide! She's coming.
大家躲起來！我看到她了，她來了
Everybody down!
大家蹲下！
Everybody stay here. I'll find out what's going on.
留在這兒，我來看看發生什麼事了
Hey, you got the door open!
嘿，你開門了！
Hey, are you drunk?
嘿，你喝醉了嗎？
No.
沒有
Okay.
好
See, I was a little nervous about turning...
我對要滿30歲…
30.
有點緊張
So the busboys took me out for some drinks.
收碗的小弟帶我去喝酒
Might want to puke on you later.
待會可能會吐在你身上
Here's the thing. We've thrown a very formal surprise party for you.
事情是這樣的 我們替你辦了一個驚喜宴會
-Your parents and friends are in there. -No!
-你的朋友和父母都在裡面 -不！
-Yes! Yes! -No.
-是的！是的！ -不
Oh, no! My parents have never seen me drunk.
哦，不！我父母從沒看我醉過
That they know of.
就他們所知
We'll get you some coffee. They'll never know that you're drunk.
我們替你弄點咖啡 他們不會知道你醉了
-You promise? -I'll take care of it.
-你確定？ -我會處理好的
I love you so much.
我好愛你
Okay, we have to do something about your breath.
好了，要對你的口臭想想辦法
What about your breath?
那你的呢？
That's still yours.
那還是你的口臭
Now remember, it's a surprise party.
記住，這是一個驚喜
So when you go in, act surprised.
你進去時要顯得很驚訝
Ready?
好了嗎？
Surprise!
驚喜！
Okay, forward. Forward.
好，前進，前進
Stop!
停止！
Okay, back.. Stop!
好，退後…停！
Okay, for.. Stop!
好，前…停！
Stop! Stop!
停！停！
Okay, here's what we're gonna do.
好，我們這麼做
I'll break into this minivan, put it in neutral.
我打開這台休旅車車門 將它放在空檔
You push it forward so Ross can get out of the spot.
你們把它向前推，羅斯就能開出來了
All right. Here we go.
好，來吧
Haul ass!
快逃！
Happy 30th birthday! Here.
30歲生日快樂！來
It's for the child in you. And the woman.
給你裡面的孩子，還有女子
Happy 30th!
30歲快樂！
Why do you keep saying that?
你為什麼一直這麼說？
Because it's our 30th birthday.
因為這是我們的30歲生日
Yeah, no, we're not 30. We're 31. Okay.
不，我們不是30，我們31歲了
Wait.
等一下
Oh, it's you.
哦，是你
Yeah. What?
是，怎麼？
Yeah, we're not 30. We're 31.
對，我們不是30，我們是31
That's what it says on my birth certificate.
我的出生證明上是這麼寫的
You have a birth certificate?
你有出生證明？
I got a big box of family stuff when my mom died.
我媽去世時，我拿到了 一箱子家庭文件
Our mom.
我們的媽
Right. Okay.
好，好
-Do you have mine? -No, I sold it to a Swedish runaway.
-你有我的嗎？ -沒有，我賣給了一個逃家的瑞典人
Oh, my God.
我的老天
Oh, my God, we are 31!
我的老天，我們31了！
Yeah.
是啊
I just lost a whole year of my life.
我失去了整整一年生命
Okay.
好
-Your middle name is Pamela? -Yes.
-你的中間名字是潘蜜拉？ -對
I never knew mine. Do you remember what it is?
我從不知道我的是什麼 你記得是什麼嗎？
Yes.
記得
Phoebe.
是菲比
-That's my first name. -Right. Okay. Then, no.
-那是我的正式名字 -對，好吧，那我不知道
We made it across the room. You're doing great.
我們成功地穿過了客廳 你做的很好
What's going on?
怎麼回事？
Monica's a little drunk.
摩妮卡有一點醉了
Yeah! I love drunk Monica.
我喜歡酒醉的摩妮卡
Oh, she's so much more fun than regular Monica.
她比正常的摩妮卡有趣多了
She doesn't want her parents to know.
她不想讓她的父母知道
All right, all right. Here's what we'll do.
好，好，我們這麼做
I'll get twice as drunk,  then no one will even notice her.
我來比她醉得厲害兩倍 就沒有人會注意她了
What's going on?
怎麼了？
Monica's wasted.
摩妮卡醉了
Maybe that'll liven up this party.
或許能讓這個宴會有點生機
Will you just help her get changed?
你能不能幫她換衣服？
Taking care of a drunk, naked woman seems like a job for Joey.
照顧酒醉，裸體的女人 好像是喬伊的工作
This one's from me.
這是我的禮物
It wasn't on your list,  but it's really fun.
這不在你的禮物單子上 不過它真的很好玩
A scooter.
滑板車
Stick to the list.
照著單子買
Always stick to the list.
永遠記得照著單子買
No, no, I love it. Thank you.
不，不，我很喜歡，謝謝
Open ours next! Open ours next!
下一個開我們的禮物！ 下一個開我們的！
Now that you're a couple,  we don't get two gifts?
你們現在是一對 我們就沒兩個禮物了？
For my last birthday,  you gave me a hug.
我上一個生日，你送我一個擁抱
Read the card! Read the card!
念卡片！念卡片！
"Happy birthday, Grandma."
生日快樂，祖母
It's better to be over the hill...
開始走下坡總比…
than buried under it.
被埋在坡下要好
"All our love, Monica and Chandler." That's funny.
我們愛你，摩妮卡和錢德 好好笑
No, no. That was a joke.
不，不，只是一個玩笑
I know, I get it. It's funny.
我知道，我懂了，很好笑
Because you're not a grandma.
因為你不是祖母
To be a grandma, you have to be married and have children.
做為一個祖母，必須結了婚有小孩
I don't have any of those things. That's why it's so funny.
我全都沒有，所以真的很好笑
I'm just gonna go...
我要…
All you had to do was buy the card.
你只需要買張卡片而己
It was stupid to get upset about not having a husband and kids.
為著沒有先生孩子就不高興，是很笨
All I really needed was a plan.
我只需要一個計劃
See, I want three kids.
我想生三個小孩
And you want to have them all at the same time and all for your brother.
你要全部同一個時候生 把他們給你弟弟
As I was saying...
我正在說…
I should have the first one by the time I'm 35.
我應該在35歲以前生第一個
Which gives me five years.
這樣我還有五年
If I want a kid when I'm 35, I don't have to get pregnant until I'm 34.
如果我35時要生孩子 我34歲時才需要懷孕
Which gives Prada four years to start making maternity clothes.
Prada還有四年時間生產孕婦裝
But I want to be married for a year before I get pregnant.
我想在懷孕之前至少結婚一年
Really? That long?
真的？要那麼久？
Look all you want, it's happening.
你愛怎麼看都行，已經在發生了
I don't have to get married until I'm 33. That's three whole years.
我到33歲再結婚就好，我還有3年
Wait a minute, though.
不過，等一下
I'll need a year and a half to plan the wedding.
我需要一年半來籌備婚禮
And I'd like to know the guy for a year, year and a half...
我希望能認識這個人一年至一年半…
before we get engaged.
再訂婚
Which means I need to meet the guy by the time I'm 30.
這表示我必須在30歲時認識這個人
Which is fine because you just turned...
沒有問題，因為你才剛剛滿…
28!
28！
No, Ross. No, it is not fine.
不，羅斯，不，有問題
I should already be with the guy I'm gonna marry.
我應該和我要嫁的對象在一起了
Will you quit hogging it?
你可不可以不要跳？
I'm telling you, it's like watching Bambi learn how to walk.
我告訴你，這就好像看著斑比學走路
You're drunk.
你醉了
Mom and Dad are gonna be mad.
爸和媽會生氣
Maybe I'm a little drunk.
也許我有一點醉了
Are those crab cakes?
那是蟹餅嗎？
I told you to come straight to me when they were ready.
我不是告訴你 蟹餅一出來立刻拿來給我？
How you feeling?
覺得怎麼樣？
You are so handsome.
你好帥
I want to make love to you right here, right now.
我想在此時此地和你上床
I really wish that you wouldn't.
我希望你不會
Just get through a little bit more, then we can put you in bed.
再撐一下，我們就可以帶你去睡覺
Just smile, and don't talk to anyone.
只要微笑，不要說話
Speech, speech! Let's hear from the birthday girl.
演講，演講！壽星演講
Phoebe!
菲比！
See, everybody's looking at me.
看，大家都在看我
The plan's working.
我的計劃很有效
I didn't even have to take off my top yet.
我還沒脫掉上衣呢
Speech. Come on, speech!
演講，演講！
You can't keep your hands off her for one second.
你連離開她一秒鐘都不行
I think it's nice.
很好啊
I think it's necessary.
我必須這樣
I want to thank you all for coming.
我要謝謝大家來到這裡
My family and...
我的家人和…
my friends.
我的朋友
I'd really like to say that I'm...
我很想說我…
You know what I'd really like to say?
知道我真的很想說什麼嗎？
I'm drunk!
我醉了！
That's right, Mom and Dad.
沒錯，爸，媽
Your little old "Harmomica" is hammered.
你們的小口琴醉了
And guess what?
猜猜怎麼著？
I've been drunk before.
我以前也喝醉過
And I've smoked a cigarette.
我抽過煙
It's all okay. It's okay because...
沒關係，沒關係，因為…
I turned 30 today.
我今天滿30歲了
And I can do anything I want.
我想做什麼就做什麼
Because I am a grownup.
因為我是成年人了
Okay, quick. Help me get this off.
好，快，替我脫掉
I lost a whole year.
我失去了整整一年
I can't believe it. This is so unfair!
真不能相信，真不公平！
Come on, Phoebe, it'll be okay.
菲比，沒有關係的
Will it? Will it?
是嗎？是嗎？
How would you feel if you found out you were 31?
如果你發現你變31歲了 你會怎麼感覺？
That's not gonna happen. Because we have a new deal.
不會的，因為我們有個新約定
Plus, it ruined my schedule.
還有，這毀了我的時間表
I haven't done the things I wanted to do before I was 31.
我還沒做那些我31歲前想做的事
-Like what? -Like I haven't met any Portuguese people.
-像什麼？ -像是我還不認識任何葡萄牙人
I haven't had the perfect kiss.
我還沒有完美地接吻過
And I haven't been to sniper school.
我還沒去上狙擊手學校
Why don't we go and have some birthday cake?
我們去吃蛋糕吧
I just feel like being by myself. See you guys later. Thanks.
我只想一個人靜一下，待會見，謝謝
Poor Phoebe.
可憐的菲比
Hey, you guys, I think I'm gonna walk her home.
嘿，知道嗎？我想我要陪她走回家
-Oh, man. -What?
-老天 -怎麼？
He's gonna eat the cake.
他會吃了蛋糕
Phoebe!
菲比！
Listen, I...
聽著，我…
Close your eyes.
閉上眼睛
That's one thing to cross off your list.
你可以將這一項從單子上劃掉
Oh, yeah.
哦，對了
Plus, I'm one-sixteenth Portuguese.
還有，我是16分之1的葡萄牙人
Okay, is everybody clear?
好，大家都清楚了？
We're gonna pick it up...
我們要將它抬起來…
and move it.
然後移動它
All we need is teamwork. We're gonna lift the car...
只需要團隊工作 我們要抬起這台車…
and slide it out.
把它滑出來
Lift...
抬起來…
and slide.
滑出來
-Ross, I really don't think this.. -Lift...
-羅斯，我真的不覺得這… -抬起來…
and slide.
滑出來
-Okay, here we go. -All right, everyone.
-好，開始吧 -好，大夥兒
Lift...
抬起來…
and slide.
移出來
-Hey, Joey.. -Come on, Rach, my turn just started.
-嘿，喬伊… -別這樣，瑞秋，才剛輪到我
Actually, I just want to talk to Tag.
其實我是要和泰格說話
Oh, okay. Hey, can I ride this outside?
哦，好，嘿，我可以到外面溜嗎？
Whatever. I'm not your mother.
隨便，我不是你媽
Not in the street!
不要到街上！
-Are you feeling any better? -Yeah, I'm doing okay. I'm...
-有沒有覺得好一點？ -有，我很好，我…
Let's talk.
我們談談
What's up?
什麼事？
Oh, Tag...
泰格…
You're such a great guy. And we have so much fun together.
你真是個好男人，我們在一起很開心
-But I.. -Wait.
-可是我… -等一下
I think I see where you're going.
我想我知道你要做什麼
Before you say anything else,  can I say one more thing?
在你說任何話之前 我可以先說一件事嗎？
Well said.
說的好
And a good example of the fun I was referring to.
正是我所謂很開心的好例子
But I think I'm past the point where I can just have fun.
但我想我已經過了只要開心的時候
Don't do this. This is just because you're turning 30.
瑞秋，不要這樣 這只是因為你30歲了
Yeah, it is.
是的
But you're just a kid. I mean, you're 25.
而你只是個孩子，你才25歲
-Twenty-four, actually. -Oh, God.
-其實是24歲 -老天
You know what I wish? I wish you were six years older.
你知道我希望什麼？ 我希望你比現在大6歲
Well, if I'm wishing for stuff,  I wish I was six years younger.
如果是希望的話 其實我希望自己年輕6歲
-Me too. -Yeah. Sorry.
-我也是 -是啊，對不起
Hey, how'd it go?
嘿，談得怎麼樣？
If I only want two kids,  can I keep him for another year?
如果我只要生兩個孩子 我可以再保留他一年嗎？
You did the right thing.
你做的對
I don't like this anymore.
我不喜歡它了
Well, here we are. Just a bunch of 30-year-olds.
我們在這兒，一群30歲的人
Do you realize in 10 years we're gonna be 40?
你知道再過10年 我們就40歲了？
Why, God?
為什麼，上帝？
Why are you doing this to us?
為什麼這麼對我們？
Yes! My baby's finally free.
太好了！我的寶貝終於自由了
All right!
好極了！
Start it up. Let's go!
啟動，我們走！
How hot are we?
我們拉不拉風？
You want to buy a car?
你要買車嗎？